<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<component type="desktop">
  <id>org.kde.kdevelop.desktop</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-2.0+</project_license>
  <name>KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="bs">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="ca">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="ca-valencia">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="cs">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="da">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="de">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="en-GB">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="es">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="et">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="fi">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="fr">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="gl">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="hu">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="it">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="nl">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="pl">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="pt">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="pt-BR">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="ru">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="sk">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="sl">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="sv">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="tr">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="uk">KDevelop</name>
  <name xml:lang="x-test">xxKDevelopxx</name>
  <name xml:lang="zh-CN">KDevelop</name>
  <summary>Featureful, plugin-extensible IDE for C/C++ and other programming languages</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ca">És un IDE, extensible amb connectors, amb totes les característiques per a C/C++ i altres llenguatges de programació.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ca-valencia">És un IDE, extensible amb connectors, amb totes les característiques per a C/C++ i altres llenguatges de programació.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="de">Eine leistungsfähige integrierte Entwicklungsumgebung (IDE) für C/C++ und andere Programmiersprachen, die durch Module erweitert werden kann.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="en-GB">Featureful, plugin-extensible IDE for C/C++ and other programming languages</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="es">Entorno de desarrollo integrado para C/C++ y otros lenguajes de programación con múltiples funcionalidades y que se puede extender con complementos.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="fr">Environnement de développement complet et extensible pour le C/C++ et d'autres langages de programmation.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="gl">Potente ambiente de desenvolvemento integrado para C, C++ e outras linguaxes de programación. As súas funcionalidades poden estenderse mediante complementos</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="it">IDE per C/C++ e altri linguaggi di programmazione completo ed estensibile</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="nl">IDE voor C/C++ en andere programmeertalen, vol functies en uit te breiden met plug-ins.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pl">Jest to w pełni funkcjonalne, z możliwością rozszerzenia przy użyciu wtyczek, zintegrowane środowisko programistyczne dla C/C++ i innych języków programowania.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pt">IDE pleno de funcionalidades e modular para o C/C++ e outras linguagens de programação</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pt-BR">IDE repleto de funcionalidades e expansível através de plugins, para C/C++ e outras linguagens de programação.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sk">Plne funkčné, pluginmi rozšíriteľné IDE pre C/C++ a iné programovacie jazyky</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sv">Funktionsrik, integrerad utvecklingsmiljö för C/C++ och andra programspråk</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="tr">Tam özellikli, eklenti ile geliştirilebilir C/C++ ve diğer programlama dilleri için tümleşik geliştirme ortamı.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="uk">Це повноцінне, розширюване за допомогою додатків комплексне середовище розробки мовами C/C++ та іншими мовами програмування.</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="x-test">xxFeatureful, plugin-extensible IDE for C/C++ and other programming languagesxx</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="zh-CN">全功能，可扩展的支持 C/C++ 和其他语言的集成开发环境。</summary>
  <description>
    <p>KDevelop is a Free and Open Source integrated development environment (IDE).</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">El KDevelop és un entorn de desenvolupament integrat (IDE) lliure i de codi obert.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca-valencia">El KDevelop és un entorn de desenvolupament integrat (IDE) lliure i de codi obert.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">KDevelop ist eine integrierte Entwicklungsumgebung (Frei und Open Source).</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">KDevelop is a Free and Open Source integrated development environment (IDE).</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">KDevelop es un entorno de desarrollo integrado (IDE) libre y de código abierto.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">KDevelop est un environnement de développement intégré (IDE) libre et en open source.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">KDevelop é un ambiente integrado de desenvolvemento (IDE) libre e de código aberto.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">KDevelop è un ambiente di sviluppo integrato (IDE) libero e open source.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">KDevelop is een vrije geïntegreerde ontwikkelomgeving (IDE) binnen het open source principe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">KDevelop to darmowe i otwartoźródłowe zintegrowane środkowisko programistyczne (IDE).</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">O KDevelop é um ambiente de desenvolvimento integrado (IDE) livre e em código aberto.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt-BR">Ambiente de Desenvolvimento Integrado (IDE) em Software Livre e Código Aberto.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">KDevelop je slobodné a otvorené integrované vývojové prostredie (IDE).</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">KDevelop är en fri integrerad utvecklingsmiljö (IDE) med öppen källkod för olika programvaruprojekt.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">KDevelop Özgür ve Açık Kaynaklı tümleşik geliştirme ortamıdır (IDE).</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">KDevelop є вільним комплексним середовищем розробки (IDE) з відкритим кодом.</p>
    <p xml:lang="x-test">xxKDevelop is a Free and Open Source integrated development environment (IDE).xx</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh-CN">可用于您的不同软件项目的自由和开源的集成开发环境</p>
    <p>It provides editing, navigation and debugging features for several programming languages, as well as integration with multiple build systems and version-control systems, using a plugin-based architecture.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">Proporciona característiques per a l'edició, navegació i depuració per a diversos llenguatges de programació, així com la integració amb múltiples sistemes de construcció i sistemes de control de versions, emprant una arquitectura basada en connectors.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca-valencia">Proporciona característiques per a l'edició, navegació i depuració per a diversos llenguatges de programació, així com la integració amb múltiples sistemes de construcció i sistemes de control de versions, emprant una arquitectura basada en connectors.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">It provides editing, navigation and debugging features for several programming languages, as well as integration with multiple build systems and version-control systems, using a plugin-based architecture.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">Proporciona funciones de edición, navegación y depuración para varios lenguajes de programación, además de integración con diversos sistemas de compilación y de control de versiones, usando una arquitectura basada en complementos.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">Il fournit des fonctionnalités d'édition, navigation et débogage pour plusieurs langages de programmation, ainsi que l'intégration de multiples systèmes de compilation et de gestion de révision, en utilisant une architecture extensible.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">Fornece funcionalidades de edición, navegación e depuración para varias linguaxes de programación, así como integración con varios sistemas de construción e sistemas de control de versións, usando unha arquitectura baseada en complementos.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Fornisce funzionalità di modifica, navigazione debug per vari linguaggi di programmazione, così come l'integrazione con vari sistemi di compilazione e di controllo versione, tramite l'uso di architettura basata sulle estensioni.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Het biedt functies voor bewerking, navigatie en debugging voor verschillende programmeertalen, evenals integratie met meerdere bouwsystemen en versiecontrole systemen, met gebruik van een op plug-ins gebaseerde architectuur.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Zapewnia możliwość edycji, poruszania się po projekcie i diagnozowania błędów dla kilku języków programistycznych, a także integrację z wieloma systemami budowania i zarządzania wersjami poprzez wbudowaną architekturę wtyczek.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">Oferece capacidades de edição, navegação e depuração para diversas linguagens de programação, assim como a integração com diversos sistemas de compilação e de controlo de versões, usando uma arquitectura baseada em 'plugins'.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">Poskytuje funkcie editovania, navigácie a ladenia pre niektoré programovacie jazyky, ako aj integráciu s viacerými zostavovacími systémami a systémami na správu verzií pomocou pluginovej architektúry.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">S pomočjo vstavkov omogoča urejanje, krmarjenje in razhroščevanje za številne programske jezike, hkrati pa ponuja podporo več sistemom za izgradnjo in nadzor različic.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">Den tillhandahåller redigerings-, navigerings- och avlusningsfunktioner för flera olika programspråk, samt integrering med ett flertal byggsystem och versionskontrollsystem, med användning av en insticksbaserad arkitektur.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">Bir çok programlama dili için düzenleme, gezinme ve hata ayıklama özellikleri sağlar, ayrıca bir çok inşa sistemi ve sürüm kontrol sistemi ile tümleşik olup eklenti-tabanlı mimari kullanır.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">У програмі передбачено можливості з редагування, навігації та діагностики коду декількома мовами програмування, а також інтеграцію із декількома системами збирання коду та керування версіями. Використовується архітектура з додатками.</p>
    <p xml:lang="x-test">xxIt provides editing, navigation and debugging features for several programming languages, as well as integration with multiple build systems and version-control systems, using a plugin-based architecture.xx</p>
    <p>KDevelop has parser backends for C, C++ and Javascript/QML, with further external plugins supporting e.g. PHP or Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">El KDevelop disposa de dorsals d'analitzador per a C, C ++ i Javascript/QML, amb altres connectors externs que implementen, p. ex., PHP o Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca-valencia">El KDevelop disposa de dorsals d'analitzador per a C, C ++ i Javascript/QML, amb altres connectors externs que implementen, p. ex., PHP o Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">KDevelop has parser backends for C, C++ and Javascript/QML, with further external plugins supporting e.g. PHP or Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">KDevelop dispone de motores de análisis sintáctico para C, C++ y JavaScript/QML, además de complementos externos (por ejemplo, para PHP o para Python).</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">KDevelop intègre des parseurs pour le C, le C++ et Javascript/QML, avec des modules externes pour prendre en charge PHP, Python, etc.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">KDevelop ten infraestruturas de análise para C, C++ e JavaScript/QML, con complementos externos adicionais que fornecen compatibilidade, por exemplo, con PHP e Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">KDevelop ha dei motori di analisi per C, C++ e JavaScript/QML, come ulteriori estensioni esterne che supportano, ad esempio, PHP o Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">KDevelop heef backends voor ontleden van C, C++ en Javascript/QML, met verdere externe plug-ins die bijv. PHP of Python ondersteunen.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">KDevelop ma silniki do przetwarzania składni C, C++ oraz Javascript/QML, a także inne jak np. PHP lub Python dodawane przy użyciu zewnętrznych wtyczek.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">O KDevelop tem infra-estruturas de processamento para C, C++ e Javascript/QML, com mais 'plugins' externos que suportam p.ex. PHP ou Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">KDevelop má backendy parsera pre C, C++ a Javascript/QML, s ďalšími externými pluginmi podporujúcimi napr. PHP alebo Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">KDevelop vsebuje razčlenjevalna zaledja za C, C++ in Javascript/QML, zunanji vstavki pa podpirajo tudi npr. PHP ali Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">KDevelop har gränssnitt för tolkning av C, C++ och Javascript/QML, med ytterligare externa insticksprogram som stöder t.ex. PHP eller Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">KDevelop C, C++ ve Javascript/QML için ayrıştırma arka uçlarına sahiptir, harici eklentilerle örn. PHP veya Python da desteklenir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">У KDevelop передбачено модулі обробки коду мовами C, C++ та Javascript/QML та додатки для розширення підтримки коду іншими мовами програмування, зокрема PHP і Python.</p>
    <p xml:lang="x-test">xxKDevelop has parser backends for C, C++ and Javascript/QML, with further external plugins supporting e.g. PHP or Python.xx</p>
  </description>
  <url type="homepage">https://kdevelop.org</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://bugs.kde.org/enter_bug.cgi?format=guided&amp;product=kdevelop</url>
  <url type="help">https://docs.kde.org/index.php?application=kdevelop</url>
  <url type="donation">https://www.kde.org/community/donations/?app=kdevelop</url>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://kde.org/images/screenshots/kdevelop.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <project_group>KDE</project_group>
  <provides>
    <binary>kdevelop</binary>
  </provides>
  <update_contact>kfunk@kde.org</update_contact>
</component>
